Guide to the Yan Sham-Shackleton Riot Grrrl Collection 1990-1999 MSS.396
Fales Library and Special Collections
Yan Sham-Shackleton Riot Grrrl Collection
1990-1999
Fales Library and Special Collections
Sham-Shackleton, Yan
MSS.396
2.6 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Yan Sham-Shackleton is a journalist, artist, and documentary filmmaker who has lived and worked in Los Angeles, Santa Cruz and New Zealand. This collection predominantly comprises zines, photographs,and ephemera she created and collected, much of it during her college years and related to feminist youth activism and theater.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Material collected and produced by Sham-Shackleton.
Series II: Media
Within each series, materials are arranged alphabetically by title.
Biographical Note
Yan Sham-Shackleton is a Hong Kong native, who now resides in Los Angeles. She lived in New Zealand as a child and traveled extensively through Australia, Asia, Europe and Central America, often taking photos. At 16 she and four female classmates in Hong Kong created a short theatre production called, "Guide to Female Logistics."
In 1997 she graduated from University of California, Santa Cruz with a B.A. in anthropology. There she participated in the majority of her riot grrrl inspired activities, such as "Women Ensemble Theater (WET)", co-directed a documentary on women and tattoos, and assisted in editing issues of the zine Yummi Hussi.
After graduation, she returned to Hong Kong where she worked as an editor and producer of Asian internet portals. In 2005 her blog "Glutter.org," was nominated for a free speech award by Reporters Without borders for her promotion of democracy in Hong Kong and China. She has participated in discussions on PBS and BBC, and at an Amnesty International conference. In 2008 she took a hiatus to stay home with her son. As he grows up, she is slowly developing new projects. In 2014 she became an editor on the well respected Reddit Thread documenting the Hong Kong Democratic Movement. Known as "The Umbrella Movement", students and citizens occupied the city center for 79 days.
Provenance
The collection was donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections by Yan Sham-Shackleton in 2014.
Scope and Content
The Yan Sham-Shackleton Riot Grrrl Collection comprises zines, photographs, and ephemera produced and collected by Sham-Shackleton in California, Hong Kong and New Zealand, as well as material produced and collected whilst studying at UC Santa Cruz, much of it related to feminist youth activism and theater.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Student projects.; Theater |z United States.; Political posters.; Posters.; Printed ephemera.; Ephemera; Picture postcards.; Punk culture.; VHS; CD-Rs.; Photographs; Riot grrrl movement.; Feminism.; Feminism and art.; Zines.
- Series I: Personal Papers, 1990-1999
  Scope and Content
  Series I predominantly consists of zines, photographs, and ephemera produced and collected by Yan Sham Shackleton in California, Hong Kong and Zealand. It also contains a scrapbook, and material produced by the Women's Ensemble Theater when Sham-Shackleton was a student at UC Santa Cruz.
  Arrangement
  Folders in this series are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "The coming of Perfection: The Posthumos Success of Sylvia Plath" Class Paper, May 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ephemera from UC Santa Cruz College Scrapbook, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Goddess" Postcard Collection, 1993-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hong Kong, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    This folder includes material collected by Sham-Shackleton when she lived in Hong Kong.
  - "Horrible/Terrible Things 1: The Pool 2: The Linesman", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - House Party Comment Book, November, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Invitation to Arlington Arts Center, Fall Solo Exhibitions, September 10, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Los Angeles, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    This folder includes material collected by Sham-Shackleton when she lived in Los Angeles.
  - New Zealand, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    This folder includes material collected by Sham-Shackleton when she lived in New Zealand.
  - Personal Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photo Album: Barbie Hall of Fame, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photo Album: Katrina Jensen editing Yummi Hussi, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photo Album: New Zealand and miscellaneus, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rolling Stone magazine, December 15, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Tattooed Dragons, Locked Doors, Backstairs and Madness" and other poems, June 1992-June 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - UC Santa Cruz College Scrapbook, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Women's Ensemble Theater, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Women's Ensemble Theater Photographs, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Yoni Zine, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Yummi Hussi Zine, Issues #5,6,7,8, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Yummi Hussi Photographs, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Media
  Series II consists of bootleg recordings of the band Hole, including printed album covers and tracklistings. It also contains an original documentary on the subject of tattoos.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access copies for some materials are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Please contact fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
  - Hole "Asking For It", April 25, 1995; ID: 396.0002; 1 media elements (Box 4, Media ID: 396.0002)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original format: CD-R
    Currently available.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Access CD available.
  - Hole "My Body, The Hand Grenade", 1997; ID: 396.0003 (Box 4, Media ID: 396.0003)
  - Hole "Under My Skin Drag", January 21, 1999; ID: 396.0004 (Box 4, Media ID: 396.0004)
  - Ouch! Documentary on tattoos as a healthy mechanism, undated; ID: 396.0001 (Box 4, Media ID: 396.0001)
    Original format: VHS
    Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
  - Laptop computer (Box 5)
- OVERSIZE Series I: Personal Papers
  Series I Oversize consists of posters, newspaper clippings, and one original artwork.
  - "Club Soda Presents Godbullies, Hole" Poster, October 30, 1996 (Map-case 3, Drawer S)
  - Body Image Art, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Feminism Newspaper Clippings, September 4, 1970; April 9, 1997; May 15, 1997; bulk (Box 3, Folder 2)
    General
    Removed from Box 2, Folder 1.
  - "The Klan Supports 209: Should You?" Poster, November, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - L.A. Poetry Festival Poster, October 25-November 1, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Removed from Box 1, Folder 8.
  - Women's Ensemble Theater Posters, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Removed from Box 2, Folder 2.